I learned about the Haiti earthquake by Skype.
لقد علمت بإمر زلزال هاييتي عبر سكاي بي.
My wife sent me a message,
أرسلت زوجتي رسالة،
"Whoa, earthquake,"
"يا إلهي، زلزال،"
and then disappeared for 25 minutes.
ثم إختفت لمدة 25 دقيقة.
It was 25 minutes of absolute terror
و كانت 25 دقيقة من الرعب التام
that thousands of people across the U.S. felt.
مر بها الاف الناس عبر الولايات المتحدة.
I was afraid of a tsunami;
كنت أخاف حدوث تسونامي.
what I didn't realize
ما لم أدركه
was there was a greater terror in Haiti,
أن الخطر في هاييتي كان أكبر من ذلك،
and that was building collapse.
خطر إنهيار المباني.
We've all seen the photos
لقد إطلعنا جميعا على صور
of the collapsed buildings in Haiti.
المباني المنهارة في هاييتي.
These are shots my wife took
هذه لقطات أخذنها زوجتي
a couple days after the quake,
بعد يومين من الزلزال،
while I was making my way through the D.R. into the country.
بينما كنت أشق انا طريقي عبر جمهورية الدومينيكان إلى داخل البلاد.
This is the national palace --
هذا هو القصر الوطني،
the equivalent of the White House.
وهو ما يعادل البيت الأبيض.
This is the largest supermarket in the Caribbean
هذا هو أكبر سوبر ماركت في منطقة الكاريبي
at peak shopping time.
وفي ذروة وقت التسوُّق.
This is a nurses' college --
وهذه كليَّة تمريض.
there are 300 nurses studying.
يدرس بها 300 ممرض/ة.
The general hospital right next door
بجوارها المستشفى العام
emerged largely unscathed.
الذي خرج من الزلزال سالماً.
This is the Ministry of Economics and Finance.
هذه هي وزارة المالية و الإقتصاد.
We have all heard
لقد سمعنا جميعاً
about the tremendous human loss
عن الخسائر البشرية الهائلة
in the earthquake in Haiti,
الناتجة عن زلزال هاييتي،
but we haven't heard enough
و لكن لم يصلنا ما يكفي
about why all those lives were lost.
عن السبب الذي أودى بحياة كل هؤلاء.
We haven't heard about
لم نسمع عما تسبب في
why the buildings failed.
إنهيار المباني.
After all, it was the buildings,
ففي نهاية الأمر، كانت المباني،
not the earthquake,
و ليس الزلزال،
that killed 220,000 people,
هي ما أودت بحياة 220.000 إنسان،
that injured 330,000,
و إصابة 330.000 آخرين،
that displaced 1.3 million people,
و تشريد 1.3 مليون فرد،
that cut off food
و تسببت في إنقطاع الغذاء
and water and supplies
و المياه و المعونات
for an entire nation.
عن أمة باكملها.
This is the largest metropolitan-area disaster
هذه أكبر كارثة تحل بتجمع حضري
in decades,
منذ قرون.
and it was not a natural disaster --
و هي لم تكن كارثة طبيعية.
it was a disaster of engineering.
بل كانت كارثة هندسية.
AIDG has worked in Haiti
لقد عملت مجموعة التطوير الملائم للبنى التحتية "AIDG" في هاييتي
since 2007,
منذ 2007 ،
providing engineering and business support
حيث تقوم بتوفير مساعدات هندسية و تجارية
to small businesses.
للمشاريع الصغيرة.
And after the quake, we started bringing in earthquake engineers
و بعد الزلزال، بدأنا في إستقطاب مهندسي زلازل
to figure out why the buildings collapsed,
ليفسروا سبب إنهيار المباني،
to examine what was safe and what wasn't.
ليقوموا بفحصها من ناحية الأمان.
Working with MINUSTAH,
خلال تعاوننا مع "MINUSTAH" بعثة الأمم المتحدة لتحقيق الاستقرار في هايتي،
which is the U.N. mission in Haiti,
وهي بعثة للأمم المتحدة في هاييتي،
with the Ministry of Public Works,
و مع وزارة العمل القومي،
with different NGOs,
ومع مختلف المنظمات غير الحكومية،
we inspected over 1,500 buildings.
قمنا بفحص أكثر من 1,500 مبنى.
We inspected schools
قمنا بفحص مباني مدرسية،
and private residencies.
و مباني سكنية.
We inspected medical centers
فحصنا المراكز الطبية
and food warehouses.
و مستودعات الطعام.
We inspected government buildings.
فحصنا المباني الحكومية.
This is the Ministry of Justice.
هذا مبنى وزارة العدل.
Behind that door
خلف هذا الباب
is the National Judicial Archives.
هو الأرشيف التشريعي الوطني.
The fellow in the door, Andre Filitrault --
الشخص الواقف عند الباب، آندريه فيليترات،
who's the director
وهو مدير مركز
of the Center for Interdisciplinary Earthquake Engineering Research
أبحاث هندسة الزلازل التخصصي
at the University of Buffalo --
في جامعة بافالو،
was examining it to see if it was safe
كان يفحص المبنى ليرى إذا كان آمناً
to recover the archives.
لإخراج سجلات الأرشيف.
Andre told me,
أخبرني آندريه،
after seeing these buildings fail
بعد رؤية هذا المبنى وهو يسقط
again and again in the same way,
مرة بعد مرة بنفس الطريقة،
that there is no new research here.
أنه لا يتم عمل أبحاث جديدة هنا.
There is nothing here that we don't know.
لا يوجد هنا ما لا نعرفه مسبقاً.
The failure points were the same:
تقاط الضعف لم تتغير --
walls and slabs not tied properly into columns --
الحوائط و الأسقف لم تدعَّم جيداً عند الأعمدة --
that's a roof slab hanging off the building --
هذا سقف معلَّق خارج المبنى --
cantilevered structures,
المباني أحادية الإرتكاز،
or structures that were asymmetric,
أو المباني الغير متماثلة،
that shook violently and came down,
التي تهتز بعنف ثم تسقط،
poor building materials,
إستخدام خامات بناء رديئة،
not enough concrete,
أسمنت غير كافي،
not enough compression in the blocks,
طوب البناء متخلل، غير منضغط بما يكفي،
rebar that was smooth,
حديد التسليح المستخدم أملس،
rebar that was exposed to the weather and had rusted away.
حديد تسليح معرَّض للعوامل الجوية و أصابه الصدأ.
Now there's a solution
الآن هناك حل
to all these problems.
لكل تلك المشكلات.
And we know how to build properly.
و نحن نعلم كيف يتم البناء بشكل صحيح.
The proof of this came in Chile,
و الدليل على هذا ظهر في تشيلي،
almost a month later,
بعد حوالي الشهر،
when 8.8 magnitude earthquake
عندما ضرب تشيلي زلزال
hit Chile.
بقوة 8.8 ريختر.
That is 500 times
وهو أقوى 500 مرة
the power of the 7.0
من قوة ال7.0 ريختر
that hit Port-au-Prince --
الذي ضرب بورتو برينس --
500 times the power,
أقوى 500 مرة،
yet only under a thousand casualties.
و مع ذلك كانت الإصابات أقل من الألف.
Adjusted for population density,
بمقارنة الكثافة السكانية،
that is less than one percent
فإن النسبة ستكون أقل من واحد بالمائة
of the impact of the Haitian quake.
من تأثير زلزال هاييتي.
What was the difference
ما الذي إختلف
between Chile and Haiti?
بين تشيلي و هاييتي؟
Seismic standards
إجراءات مواجهة الزلازل
and confined masonry,
و الأبنية الإحتوائية،
where the building acts as a whole --
حيث يعمل المبنى كوحدة واحدة --
walls and columns
الحوائط و الأعمدة
and roofs and slabs
الأسقف و الأرضيات
tied together to support each other --
كلها مترابطة داعمة لبعضها البعض،
instead of breaking off into separate members and failing.
بدلا من أن تتحطم إلى اجزاء منفصلة و تسقط.
If you look at this building in Chile,
إذا نظرتم إلى هذا المبنى في تشيلي،
it's ripped in half,
إنه منقسم إلى نصفين،
but it's not a pile of rubble.
و لكنه ليس كومة حطام.
Chileans have been building with confined masonry
كان أهل شيلي يعتمدون طريقة البناء الإحتوائي
for decades.
منذ عقود.
Right now, AIDG is working with KPFF Consulting Engineers,
حاليا تتعاون "AIDG" مجموعة التطوير الملائم للبنى التحتية مع KPFF للإستشارات الهندسية،
Architecture for Humanity,
و مؤسسة "آركيتكتشر فور هيومانيتي"
to bring more confined masonry training
لإدخال المزيد من التدريب على البناء الإحتوائي
into Haiti.
إلى هاييتي.
This is Xantus Daniel;
هذا هو "إكزانتوس دانييل".
he's a mason,
وهو عامل بناء،
just a general construction worker, not a foreman,
فقط عامل بناء عادي و ليس رئيس عمال،
who took one of our trainings.
وقد أخذ أحد دروسنا التدريبية.
On his last job he was working with his boss,
في آخر أعماله و بينما هو يعمل مع رئيسه،
and they started pouring the columns wrong.
بدأوا في صب الأعمدة بشكل خاطئ.
He took his boss aside,
فأخذ رئيسه جانباً،
and he showed him the materials on confined masonry.
و عرض عليه الخامات المستخدمة في البناء الإحتوائي.
He showed him, "You know, we don't have to do this wrong.
و أوضح قائلا: "أتعلم، لسنا في حاجة لإستخدام الطريقة الخاطئة.
It won't cost us any more
لن تكون التكلفة أكثر
to do it the right way."
لو إستخدمنا الطريقة الصحيحة."
And they redid that building.
و قد أعادوا بناء ذلك المبنى.
They tied the rebar right,
و ربطوا حديد التسليح بطريقة صحيحة.
they poured the columns right,
وصبوا الأعمدة بطريقة صحيحة.
and that building will be safe.
و هذا البناء سيكون آمناً.
And every building
و كل مبنى سيقومون
that they build going forward
ببناءه من الآن فصاعداً
will be safe.
سيكون آمناً.
To make sure these buildings are safe,
التأكد من تأمين تلك المباني
it's not going to take policy --
لن يتطلب أعمالاً سياسية،
it's going to take reaching out
بل يتطلب التواصل مع
to the masons on the ground
عمال البناء في المواقع
and helping them learn the proper techniques.
و مساعدتهم على تعلُّم طرق البناء الصحيحة.
Now there are many groups doing this.
الآن هناك العديد من المجموعات تبنت هذه الطريقة.
And the fellow in the vest there,
و هذا الرجل ذو الصديري هناك،
Craig Toten,
"كرايغ توتين"
he has pushed forward
قام بمساعٍ عدة
to get documentation out to all the groups that are doing this.
لإستخراج تصاريح لكل تلك المجموعات التي تعمل بها.
Through Haiti Rewired,
من خلال "هاييتي ري-وايرد"،
through Build Change, Architecture for Humanity,
و "بيلد تشانج" و "آركيتكتشر فور هيومانيتي"،
AIDG,
و "AIDG" مجموعة التطوير الملائم للبنى التحتية،
there is the possibility
أصبحت هناك إمكانية
to reach out
للتواصل مع
to 30,000 -- 40,000 masons
30.000 ، 40.000 عامل بناء
across the country
عبر البلاد
and create a movement of proper building.
وبداية نهضة لطرق البناء الصحيحة.
If you reach out to the people on the ground
فإذا تواصلت مع العمال في مواقع البناء
in this collaborative way
بهذه الطريقة التعاونية
it's extremely affordable.
سيكون الأمر محتملا جداً مادياً.
For the billions spent on reconstruction,
بالبلايين التي تُنفق على إعادة البناء،
you can train masons
يمكنك تدريب عمال بناء
for dollars on every house
مقابل بضع دولارات لكل منزل
that they end up building over their lifetime.
يبنونه بتلك الطريقة طوال حياتهم.
Ultimately, there are two ways
في نهاية الأمر، هناك طريقتين
that you can rebuild Haiti;
لإعادة بناء هاييتي،
the way at the top
الطريقة العليا
is the way that Haiti's been building for decades.
هي الطريقة التي إتبعتها هاييتي لعقود طويلة.
The way at the top
الطريقة العليا هي
is a poorly constructed building
مباني ضعيفة الهيكل
that will fail.
مصيرها السقوط.
The way at the bottom is a confined masonry building,
الطريقة السفلى هي طريقة البناء الإحتوائي،
where the walls are tied together,
حيث الحوائط مترابطة جيداً
the building is symmetric,
و البناء متماثل
and it will stand up to an earthquake.
و سوف يصمد أمام الزلازل.
For all the disaster,
أمام هذه الكارثة
there is an opportunity here
هناك فرصة هنا
to build better houses
لبناء مبانيٍ أفضل
for the next generation,
للأجيال القادمة،
so that when the next earthquake hits,
بحيث ما إن يضرب الزلزال التالي
it is a disaster --
نعم سيكون كارثة،
but not a tragedy.
و لكن لن يصبح مأساة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)